<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-10T11:51:30+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">academic writing resources</title><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/academic-writing-resources/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="academic writing resources"/><published>2024-12-30T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-30T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/academic-writing-resources</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/academic-writing-resources/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="academic-writing-resourcesß">Academic writing resourcesß</h1> <p>I’ve collected a few resources over the years to help with any academic writing tasks, from assignments for class through to research papers. I would recommend branching out further than your own specific area of interest and seeing how other fields organise their work, as there may be someone doing something completely different to you that you could learn a lot from!</p> <h2 id="general">General</h2> <p>I’d recommend speaking to your nearest library team about this sort of thing. They’re experts in knowing which resources to go to, and often run workshops or drop-ins where you can practice and learn more. For students this will likely be your university library, but don’t sleep on your hospital library either, if you have access! I’ve attended many a Zoom workshop covering critical analysis, source finding and lots of other useful skills via my hospital library whilst at medical school.</p> <p>Here are a couple of examples of what to look for:</p> <ol> <li>My current NHS Trust, UHL, has the following sessions available at the library: [link to training calendar] (https://www.uhl-library.nhs.uk/trainingcalendar.html)</li> <li>Same thing at the hospital I was based at during university: <a href="https://www.uhsussex.nhs.uk/professionals/knowledge-and-libraries/information-skills-teaching/">University Hospitals Sussex</a></li> </ol> <p>To find these, you can google “{your hospital trust} + library services” and follow the links. If you’re having difficulty just pop them an email or visit in person!</p> <p>There’s also lots of different individuals with useful websites.</p> <p><a href="https://www.raulpacheco.org/">Dr Raul Pacheco-Vega</a> is a Full Professor in the Methods Lab of the Latin American Faculty for Social Sciences (Facultad Latinoamericana de Ciencias Sociales, FLACSO) Sede México. His website not only covers his interdisciplinary work but also includes a massive amount of advice and useful resources for anyone with academic writing tasks. From organising your work to the actual reading and writing, I’d recommend browsing through.</p> <p><a href="https://x.com/VnVrinda">Vrinda Nair</a> is a doctoral candidate at Concordia University. She has a great Twitter/X page sharing thoughts and resources to help with all aspects of academic life, from writing resources to advice on choosing colour schemes for maximum impact when presenting. There are so many threads here full of advice, have a browse.</p> <h2 id="gathering-sources">Gathering sources</h2> <p><a href="https://www.connectedpapers.com/">Connected Papers</a> is a wonderful site where for any academic paper, you can find links to others. Covering both papers referenced by your one, as well as papers which reference it, it’s a good way to get an initial handle on a field.</p> <h2 id="writing">Writing</h2> <p>Once you get to writing, <a href="https://www.phrasebank.manchester.ac.uk/">Phrasebank</a> by <a href="https://www.phrasebank.manchester.ac.uk/dr-john-morley/">Dr John Morley</a> from the University of Manchester has some excellent sentence frameworks and starters. If you’re asking the question “how do I phrase this professionally?”, “how do I say this concisely?” - this is a good place to start.</p> <h2 id="referencing">Referencing</h2> <p>I’m a fan of <a href="https://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</a> personally (especially now you can read PDFs in-app!), but this will also depend on specific projects - especially if you’re collaborating with others, it is worth it to familiarise yourself with different reference managers.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="advice,"/><category term="academic-writing"/><category term="academic-writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[for all your academic writing needs]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">DRAFT clinical academic training</title><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/clinical-academic-training/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DRAFT clinical academic training"/><published>2024-12-30T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-30T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/clinical-academic-training</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/clinical-academic-training/"><![CDATA[<p>I get a lot of questions from medical students and more junior doctors in their foundation years about clinical academic training, so I thought I’d address some points here. Hopefully you find it useful in planning your own career.</p> <h1 id="clinical-academic-training-what-is-it">Clinical academic training: what is it?</h1> <p>Broadly, clinical academic training is a way of generating clinical doctors as well as other clinicians who are also able to conduct research and work in higher education settings, for example as Professors.</p> <p>This post will focus on the UK context, as well as the medical context - i.e. this will cover the career pathway for medical doctors. It should also be noted that these pathways are constantly changing as the medical workforce planning in the UK is under constant discussion, and I’ll do my best to keep this as up-to-date as possible.</p> <p>It is also important to note that whilst this will cover the training pathway in a linear fashion, it’s not always going to be linear for everyone. It’s easiest to present the information like this but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Map%E2%80%93territory_relation">the map is not the terrain</a> and lots of people have taken lots of different routes to get to similar places.</p> <p>In essence, you can think of clinical academic training as an ‘add-on’ to your usual medical training. You apply for posts at the same time and through the same channels as usual (that’s Oriel), and you need to meet your clinical training requirements as well.</p> <p>The earliest place to get involved is through the Specialised Foundation Programme or <a href="https://foundationprogramme.nhs.uk/programmes/2-year-foundation-programme/specialised-foundation-programme/">SFP</a>. This is organised through the UK Foundation Programme Organisation or UKFPO, and you’ll apply at the same time as your normal FP application. Please read through the various parts of the website carefully - the process for 2025 changed recently, and nobody has experience of it yet.</p> <p>The SFP follows the same pattern as any other FP: 6 rotations over 2 years lasting 4 months each. These may be in any specialty, but should usually include a mix of medical and surgical work. The SFP will give you a certain amount of protected academic time - this will usually be either day release or a whole academic block. What academic time covers will be discussed below.</p> <p>After the SFP, you’ll apply for specialty training. At this stage, you’ll also be able to apply for an <a href="https://www.nihr.ac.uk/career-development/research-career-funding-programmes/predoctoral/academic-clinical-fellowship">Academic Clinical Fellowship</a>, funded by the NIHR (National Institute for Health and Care Research). This will be a separate application process</p> <h1 id="academic-time">Academic time?</h1> <p>So what do you actually <em>do</em> during your academic time? This will depend on your project(s), and your supervisor. It will also depend on the way your time is organised - day release, block release or some combination.</p> <p>During the SFP, you’ll likely be stratified into research, education or leadership tracks, which will influence your use of academic time. Education tracks will likely be doing some sort of teaching activity, revision course, simulation or similar. Research tracks will likely be doing more traditional research, for example gathering and analysing data, writing up findings and creating publications/presentations. Leadership is the track I’m least personally familiar with, but I understand it to be more along the lines of management, for example quality improvements or safety.</p> <h2 id="advantages">Advantages</h2> <p>“But Anna,” I hear you cry, “aren’t these all activities I can do <em>without</em> academic time dedicated to them?”</p> <p>Essentially, yes. I did these sorts of things at medical school without protected time, and of course things like quality improvement projects are mandatory throughout training (ask your nearest doctor, and prepare for a rant). However, when you do these things, <em>you’re not being paid to do them</em>. I’ll let you think what you will about that. You’re also having to do them in the evenings and on weekends, or other times you might want to spend resting. In summary, academic time isn’t necessary to do these activities - I knew someone who got a part-time Masters in Medical Education during FY1-FY2 - but it does make it easier.</p> <p>It also gives you time away from the wards, which anyone will tell you is a good thing. It means when you go back, you’re refreshed. It means you have a wider awareness of issues around the healthcare system rather than getting tunnel vision regarding your day-to-day. It protects you from getting burned out by the repetitive nature of some major clinical challenges - instead of having to face the misery of the A+E waiting room 10 times a shift only to see the same people waiting in corridors when you get back to work the next day, you get some time to focus on something you actually enjoy doing.</p> <p>For me, it reinforces the distinction between <em>job</em> and <em>career</em>. Yes, the day-to-day job has its ups and downs. But it helps to see certain hoops as just that - hoops to jump through to get to a better place, rather than seeing them as essentials to your work and sense of self.</p> <h2 id="disadvantages">Disadvantages</h2> <p>“Sounds amazing, I’m sold - but isn’t this too good to be true?” Another excellent point. There are certainly challenges associated with this. The main one, and if you don’t acknowledge your awareness of this in your white space questions or interviews (see <a href="#applying">Applying</a>) below, you’re not going to convince anyone you’re prepared, is the impact it has on your clinical training.</p> <p>Any clinical training has certain outcomes you need to meet. In FY1 and FY2 these are broad and generalisable - assessing sick patients, starting management, communicating well. I’m in O+G training now, and this year I need to demonstrate ability to take a cervical smear, and by the end of training I’ll be expected to be able to do more advanced things like complicated C sections. The requirements get gradually more demanding. Someone like me who is given 75% clinical and 25% academic time is still working full time (48h/week for doctors).</p> <p>This means my training will still take the same amount of time as my 100% clinical colleagues. In other words, I have <em>75% of the time they do</em> to reach <em>the same exact outcomes</em>.</p> <p>In contrast to someone working less than full time (LTFT) at 75% pro-rata, who will have their training extended to compensate for the additional time away from their clinical work. Yes, we’ll both have the same amount of clinical time, but they will have longer to meet the requirements than me.</p> <p>That’s the main disadvantage, and there are others. Because you’re not working the same amount of time clinically, some old-fashioned miserable people will dislike you and think you don’t take the job seriously. LTFT trainees get the same. Not all departments are like this - my current teams are all lovely - but in previous rotations and speaking to other doctors, it’s definitely not an uncommon attitude in some places. Ask at your interview, or talk to existing trainees.</p> <h1 id="applying">Applying</h1> <p>So now we get to the application.</p> <h1 id="more-information">More information</h1> <p>Please do also feel free to message me via any of the contact details on this website and I’ll do my best to answer your questions!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="advice"/><category term="clinical-academia,"/><category term="career"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[what is it? and what's the point?]]></summary></entry></feed>