<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-13T07:36:33+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">BGCS Annual Scientific Meeting 2025</title><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/BGCS2025/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="BGCS Annual Scientific Meeting 2025"/><published>2025-07-11T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-11T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/BGCS2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/BGCS2025/"><![CDATA[<p>Today I attended the <a href="https://www.bgcs.org.uk/">British Gynaecological Cancer Society</a>’s 2025 <a href="https://www.bgcs.org.uk/event/asm-london-2025/#menu-item-1204_">Annual Scientific Meeting</a></p> <div style="text-align: center;"><img src="/assets/img/canvas.png" width="300"/></div> <p>I could only attend the last day due to my shift pattern, which was a shame, but it was really enjoyable nevertheless.</p> <ol> <li>Multidisciplinary working in gynae-oncology <ul> <li>I really liked hearing from different surgical specialties about how they are involved in gyn-onc surgeries, what sort of skills they can offer and advice for working together for patients</li> <li>There’s honestly so much cool surgery happening that I didn’t fully realise, and still don’t altogether understand</li> <li>It’s heartening to see that we’re not mortal enemies of the urologists!</li> </ul> </li> <li>Novel Technologies and Strategies <ul> <li>Very interesting to see the breadth of different approaches to questions in gynae-oncology</li> <li>I had never heard of HIPEC or PIPAC so that was really eye opening</li> </ul> </li> <li>Short oral presentations <ul> <li>Rapid presentations (each was 5 mins long) which I really enjoyed as a quick overview of a range of gynae-oncology topics</li> <li>Obviously my favourite was the one on ctDNA in endometrial cancer, but I also really liked the presentation of the FAIR-O study, looking at frailty assessment which is something I remember being emphasised in my surgical FY1 rotation</li> </ul> </li> </ol> <p>I also met representatives of <a href="https://peachestrust.org/">Peaches womb cancer trust</a>, which is a wonderful resource both for researchers like me to keep the work grounded and linked to people actually experiencing the disease, but also to signpost patients to in clinic.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="academic"/><category term="presentation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[a poster is presented, and talks are attended]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Starting in research</title><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/starting-in-research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starting in research"/><published>2025-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/starting-in-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/starting-in-research/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="research-in-medical-school---actually-doing-it">Research in medical school - actually doing it</h1> <p>So you’ve been invited to join in with a research project, but don’t know where to start. Don’t worry. It’s all about gaining new skills and using them, and before you know it you’re going to be an asset to your team.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="basic-skills">Basic skills</h1> <p>There are a couple of skills which you’ll need before starting any work in the world of research. These aren’t skills like statistical analysis which you’ll learn ‘on-the-job’, but skills you should have at least a vague understanding of before starting.</p> <h2 id="reading">Reading</h2> <p>Reading is… fundamental! It’s important you know how to read a paper, how to critically appraise literature, and are able to quickly find your way around new topics. Here’s some help.</p> <p>If you google ‘how to read a paper’, it’ll show you some helpful places to start.</p> <p>Prof. Trisha Greenhalgh’s book <a href="https://www.bmj.com/content/315/7112/891.1">How to Read a Paper</a> is a book which I think everyone apart from me has read, and it seems to be a good starting point. There’s also this <a href="https://www.bmj.com/about-bmj/resources-readers/publications/how-read-paper">series of articles</a> in the BMJ which look useful.</p> <p>If reading isn’t your jam, I can recommend the <a href="https://www.theresusroom.co.uk/category/podcasts/">Resus Room</a> podcast which has a monthly journal club episode. It’s EM-focussed, so not always the most relevant, but always a useful glimpse at what to look at when judging how relevant a paper will be to clinical practice.</p> <p>In fact, any journal club will be really useful here, as it’ll get you a) reading lots, and b) discussing paper quality which is important to the critical appraisal process. If you don’t have a journal club at your university, consider setting one up.</p> <p>There are also several online tools, such as <a href="https://casp-uk.net/casp-tools-checklists/">CASP</a> which offer things like checklists for assessing evidence quality. The <a href="https://jbi.global/critical-appraisal-tools">Joanna Briggs Institute, JBI</a> is another example.</p> <p>You can also read the evidence section of NICE guidelines (<a href="https://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng133/evidence">here</a>’s the one for hypertension in pregnancy) where the organisation outlines things like the searches it used, the criteria it assessed for and so on. This is useful for linking academic writing to clinical practice.</p> <p>It can also be helpful to use the full range of library schemes you have access to as a medical student. When I was at university, I was part of the University of Brighton library, the University of Sussex library, the BSMS library and my local NHS Trust library. This meant I had 4 routes to finding resources I needed; 4 places to ask for academic support; and (annoyingly), 4 logins to juggle.</p> <p>I’m now affiliated with the University of Leicester and University Hospitals of Leicester NHS Trust - 2 excellent libraries which can both offer support in finding and accessing resources.</p> <p>In terms of finding papers, resources like <a href="https://www.connectedpapers.com/">Connected Papers</a> are so useful in mapping new areas of research. This is a website with a free tier (when I first used it back in 2019 it was completely free, so how times have changed!) where it shows you papers linked to any paper you tell it, what is often referenced, what often references it (i.e. what came before and what is happening afterwards), and is just good for a quick understanding of a new topic. Works best when you plug in a key paper, and is also good for identifying those key papers.</p> <h2 id="writing">Writing</h2> <p>The more you read, the better you’ll write, so these two skills are very deeply linked.</p> <p>Writing is something you’ll hopefully be doing fairly often at university in the form of essays and so on, and there are a few skills which will help make this as easy as possible.</p> <p>I like <a href="https://www.phrasebank.manchester.ac.uk/">PhraseBank</a> from the University of Manchester, and would recommend my page on <a href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/academic-writing-resources/">Academic Writing</a> for more resources.</p> <p>I also find that the more seamless my referencing workflow, the easier it is to get ideas to paper without worrying about where the information is coming from. With the appropriate browser extensions, referencing software and word processor plugins, you’re literally a few clicks away from writing about papers you find.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="less-basic-skills">Less basic skills</h1> <p>There are a couple of skills which can be useful to develop, but are definitely not essential and won’t be relevant to all projects.</p> <h2 id="systematic-reviews">Systematic reviews</h2> <p>If you’re working on a systematic review, which I’d recommend as a good starting point, I cannot recommend Covidence or Rayyan (open source version) highly enough. They are both websites which allow for screening of resources collaboratively, and just really make the whole experience so much easier. Import some to each, have a play around with a second account, and see how much easier it is than managing things manually.</p> <h2 id="statistical-analysis">Statistical analysis</h2> <p>If you’re affiliated with a university, chances are you have free access to a range of software packages. If your project needs someone to work out p-values, it’s worth seeing if you can familiarise yourself with e.g. Stata, R, or Python for data analysis. There are also online resources for learning how to do this in any language. Check out YouTube for tutorials, the documentation for whichever language you’re using, or things like <a href="https://www.freecodecamp.org/">FreeCodeCamp</a> for further education.</p> <h2 id="qualitative-analysis">Qualitative analysis</h2> <p>Similar to the above, learning how to use software like NVivo really broadens your skillset and ability to approach research questions. No longer will you be frustrated at your inability to understand the nuance around a quantitative paper - when you have the skills to add a qualitative dimension. Get a dataset, play around, and develop your toolkit for approaching questions.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="putting-it-all-together">Putting it all together</h1> <p>I hope this gives you somewhere to start, and improves your confidence in putting yourself forward to get involved as a collaborator or co-author. Even if your project doesn’t get published, these are all useful skills which will help throughout your work and education.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="drafts,"/><category term="templates"/><category term="clinical-academic-training,"/><category term="career"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[where to start?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">MRCOG reflections</title><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/MRCOG-reflections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MRCOG reflections"/><published>2025-02-03T13:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-03T13:36:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/MRCOG-reflections</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/MRCOG-reflections/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve got my MRCOG part 1 exam on the 1st of July this year. With that in mind, I’d like to document my approach to this so once I have my result I can learn from it for whichever exam I need to sit next.</p> <h1 id="strategy">Strategy</h1> <h2 id="domains">Domains</h2> <p>Not all the domains in the exam are created equal. With that in mind, I’ve made a list in order of size (based on the pie charts in the first chapter of the <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/abs/mrcog-part-one/your-essential-revision-guide-mrcog-part-one/50E01B02017A3AA543EFD5DA556A05FF">Essential Guide</a>).</p> <h2 id="qbanks-and-anki">Qbanks and Anki</h2> <p>I’ve then got some subscriptions to question banks, and based on the list of domains, I go through the topics in the banks. For example, I’ll do anatomy first, and microbiology a few domains later as it’s not as heavily weighted.</p> <p>When I do my questions, I create Anki flashcards as I go based on 3 things:</p> <ol> <li>Things I get wrong (obvious)</li> <li>Things I get <em>right</em>, but where I don’t know important reasoning behind the answers</li> <li>Things that keep coming up (so they must be important, right?)</li> </ol> <p>I then do my Anki daily. I have a streak, and it’s motivating to keep it going. The benefit of this is that I see things I get wrong more often, more often - thanks to spaced repetition - so I’m not using up question bank questions on this.</p> <p>I <em>don’t do</em> the Qbanks daily. Each block of around 100 questions takes a while (depending on domain and repetition of themes), especially when making flashcards properly, so I tend to only do this on standard days or days off.</p> <h2 id="mocks">Mocks</h2> <p>I do a mock roughly once per month, at the end of the month, to track progress and practice under closer-to-exam conditions (i.e. not doing flashcards at the gym). I’m planning to spend June doing basically straight mocks rather than practice questions, in hopes that this will help get me into the right mindset and practicing exam technique.</p> <h2 id="courses">Courses</h2> <p>I’m planning on attending the RCOG course for the part 1. My colleagues have mentioned other courses, so we will see.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="challenges">Challenges</h1> <p>I’m documenting what I think my main challenges are, so I can see how I view this in a few years’ time.</p> <h2 id="time">Time</h2> <p>As a doctor in the NHS, you’re working 48h on average per week. Unlike at university, you’re expected to revise for these major exams at the same time as working clinically. This is a challenge. On weeks where I have night shifts, I am pleased if I get a few Anki questions just to keep my streak, rather than focussing on doing loads.</p> <h2 id="clinical-relevance">Clinical relevance</h2> <p>I think it would be easier if the information I need to know for the MRCOG Part 1 was more clinically relevant in the day-to-day job. Things like embryology, or amino acids, are just not things that affect the ward round, discharge summaries, surgery lists or any of the other jobs my fellow SHOs and myself do. Of course they can be made to be relevant - for example reviewing developmental stages and how medications can affect things at different gestations, but this exam is more theoretical than applied, so my day-to-day doesn’t really prompt on-the-job revision.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="obgyn"/><category term="job,"/><category term="MRCOG"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[revising during work]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">research at medical school - meeting people</title><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/meeting-people/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="research at medical school - meeting people"/><published>2025-02-02T12:18:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-02T12:18:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/meeting-people</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/meeting-people/"><![CDATA[<p>I had a bunch of medical students asking about research experience in medical school, and how to go about it, so I wanted to share some general thoughts and strategies. This will depend on things like your own personal time (if you have children, a job, or caring responsibilities then these will be more challenging), as well as your university and access to mentors or supervisors.</p> <p>Firstly, it should be noted that publications and presentations count for 2 different portfolio scoring sections; and that oral and poster presentations also count for different sections (though this can vary, check your specialty scoring details for more information). With this in mind, the ideal situation is doing one project that nets you multiple outputs - you might initially present it as a poster at a conference, then go on to publish it.</p> <p>It should also be on your radar that not every project is going to lead anywhere. It is worth being upfront with supervisors. Something like “I’m interested in X/Y/Z specialty/area/method, and I want to maximise my competitiveness. I already have poster and oral presentations so would need a publication from this project.” - immediately your supervisor is aware of where you’re coming from, your priorities etc. and can be honest about how likely this is to avoid wasting time.</p> <p>The absolute main points are probably these: connections and time.</p> <p>The more people you know, the more likely they are to suggest opportunities to you. And the longer you give yourself to do things, the more time you have to accumulate success. Start early!</p> <hr/> <h1 id="student-groups">Student groups</h1> <p>There will be local ones at your university, as well as some national ones. Google them!</p> <p>Some to get you started:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://www.incisionuk.com/">InciSioN UK</a></li> <li><a href="https://starsurg.org/">STARSurg</a></li> <li><a href="https://studentsforglobalhealth.org/">Students for Global Health</a></li> <li><a href="https://bursturology.com/">BURST Urology</a></li> </ul> <p>Find whatever interests you. These are great for a few reasons.</p> <ul> <li>Meeting people! <ul> <li>If you’re part of one of these groups or student societies, chances are you’re interested in the specialty. This means you can meet others who are also interested! Work with them, take advice from those further along the road than yourself, and see what’s out there!</li> </ul> </li> <li>Opportunities <ul> <li>These groups routinely produce research outputs. Audits, papers, posters etc., this is the place to get involved in the developing knowledge in your specialty of interest, and get your name out there</li> </ul> </li> <li>Learning <ul> <li>Do you actually want to do this specialty? Are you genuinely interested? Getting stuck in is the best way to find out if this is something you want to do! If you decide “hey, I hate surgery” - fantastic! At least you found out now rather than midway through CST</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h1 id="faculty-clinicians-and-students">Faculty, clinicians and students</h1> <p>These are also great! Chances are, if you’re at a university, you’re linked to a university hospital. This means you’ll have professors, faculty members, and clinical academics surrounding you. Approach them!</p> <p>Ideas:</p> <ul> <li>Ask a lecturer <ul> <li>If they’re teaching you cool stuff, they’re probably doing cool stuff on the side. Ask them if they need an extra pair of hands/eyes and offer your help. Even if they say no, they’ll be thinking of you if an opportunity arises</li> </ul> </li> <li>Ask a consultant <ul> <li>If you know what specialty you’re interested in, on placement find a nice consultant and ask them if they know about any studies or projects happening in the department</li> </ul> </li> <li>Ask other students <ul> <li>If you’ve got student-selected aspects (e.g. SSCs) or similar, find students who are doing things in areas you’re interested in! They are at a very similar stage to you, and will likely have learning points which are very relevant and actionable</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <h1 id="conferences">Conferences</h1> <p>Similar to the student groups, if you’re attending one of these it’s likely you’re interested in the topic. Make connections, exchange LinkedIn profiles or whatever the cool kids do these days, and find out what’s new!</p> <p>If you see a cool poster, reach out to the person who made it! If you attend an interesting talk, ask some questions afterwards. If you’re a student, people will understand you might not have all the answers, and will hopefully be happy to offer advice and insights. Ask about their journeys - people take all sorts of paths to get to where they are, and it’s useful to have a broader understanding of career options than just those presented at university.</p> <h1 id="other-approaches">Other approaches</h1> <p>OK, so a lot of the above will be online, especially things like conferences. It’s worth thinking outside the box though, and using social media, LinkedIn and other forums where you can find people doing interesting things. Think things like authors on publications, or even the news! I used to work with someone who did some really cool research with a team he made contact with after seeing them on the news!</p> <hr/> <h1 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping up</h1> <p>I hope this has given you something to think about and some approaches to getting to know people which will help you get started with some research involvement. Please reach out to me if you think I have anything to add!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="advice"/><category term="career-advice"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[how do people even do this?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">commitment (to specialty) issues</title><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/commitment-to-specialty/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="commitment (to specialty) issues"/><published>2025-01-18T12:27:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-18T12:27:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/commitment-to-specialty</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/commitment-to-specialty/"><![CDATA[<p>“Commitment to specialty” is something people ask about at all stages of medical school, and some aspects are way easier to manage if you start them early. Let’s get into it.</p> <h1 id="cst-and-other-surgical-ambitions">CST and other surgical ambitions</h1> <p>The <a href="https://medical.hee.nhs.uk/medical-training-recruitment/medical-specialty-training/surgery/core-surgery/core-surgical-training-self-assessment-scoring-guidance-for-candidates">2025 CST portfolio scoring guidelines</a> are out, and you should have a look at them.</p> <p>To maximise your points in this section, you’ll need verified logbook evidence of over 40 cases, as well as one of: at least 5 taster days (total), at least 4 weeks on an elective, or a FY placement in a surgical specialty.</p> <p>I think the main problem here is the cases, to be honest. Firstly, everyone should have a surgical rotation in FY, and if you don’t, organising 5 non-consecutive taster days shouldn’t be too difficult. If you get a relevant elective sorted, even easier.</p> <h2 id="the-cases---the-uk-pan-surgical-logbook">The cases - the UK pan-surgical logbook</h2> <p>The <a href="https://www.elogbook.org/">Pan-Surgical Electronic Logbook for the United Kingdom and Ireland</a> is what you’ll need to demonstrate involvement in ≥40 cases. NB <em>“Involvement” means “scrubbed in” - not observing.</em></p> <p>Steps as follows:</p> <ol> <li>make an account (straightforward)</li> <li>start recording cases (relatively straightforward, fun fact! gynaecological procedures and C-sections count as general surgery)</li> <li>get those cases signed off (complicated)</li> </ol> <p>The most complicated bit will be the validation/sign off. Go to “browse operations” –&gt; “request trainer validation”. You can also, for trainers who are not as technologically adept/up to date/registered on the elogbook etc., print off the list and get a physical signature.</p> <p>Then scan these in and save them as a PDF ready to upload as evidence.</p> <p>Happy scrubbing!</p> <h1 id="imt-and-other-medical-specialties">IMT and other medical specialties</h1> <p>IMT does not use commitment to specialty in the <a href="https://www.imtrecruitment.org.uk/recruitment-process/applying/application-scoring">2025 guidance</a></p> <p><a href="https://medical.hee.nhs.uk/medical-training-recruitment/medical-specialty-training/pathology/histopathology/overview-of-histopathology/histopathology-training-self-assessment-scoring-guidance-for-applicants">Histopathology</a>: 3+ days taster, or an FY rotation/’extended period of training’ (who knows what that means). You also get separate points for ‘histopathology-related activities’ which appear to be a related publication and/or presentation.</p> <h1 id="overall">Overall</h1> <p>Other than these examples, it is worth finding out what your specialty of choice looks for - if anything. If you start optimising your portfolio now, it’ll be one less thing to worry about closer to the time.</p> <p>Generally, attending things like conferences, getting involved in student groups, and making the most of any opportunities is a good strategy. The more people you meet who are doing things in the area you’re interested in, the more people you have to ask for advice.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="advice"/><category term="portfolio,"/><category term="career-advice"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[proving your devotion]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">how to maximise your CV for medical specialty applications</title><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/CV-maxxing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how to maximise your CV for medical specialty applications"/><published>2025-01-13T12:34:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-13T12:34:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/CV-maxxing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/CV-maxxing/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="update-jan-2025">UPDATE Jan 2025:</h2> <p>no sooner had I posted this than the CST portfolio assessment has been updated again! The links in this article will take you to the latest guidance, and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20221102132123/https://medical.hee.nhs.uk/medical-training-recruitment/medical-specialty-training/surgery/core-surgery/core-surgical-training-self-assessment-scoring-guidance-for-candidates">here</a> is the previous one for historical reference.</p> <hr/> <p>One of the major stresses for any medical student or doctor in the UK looking at entering specialty training is your portfolio. And I don’t mean Horus! What is a portfolio? What needs to go in it? What looks good? And most importantly: how can I maximise the usefulness of my time spent working hard on all these extra things?</p> <p>Disclaimer: I am NOT suggesting my CV is particularly incredible. I have had a lot of guidance from various sources and learnt along the way, so the point of this is more to share some of my experiences and approaches, rather than being some sort of guarantee of success.</p> <p>Onwards!</p> <h1 id="part-1-what-goes-into-a-medical-cv-or-portfolio">Part 1: what goes into a medical CV or portfolio?</h1> <p>For this we first look to the BMJ: <a href="https://www.bmj.com/content/343/bmj.d5289">Preparing the perfect medical CV</a> by Green, 2011. I know it’s like 100 years old. The important thing here is that it’s <em>transferable</em>. None of these headings are specific to any specialty, it’s all completely template.</p> <p>My advice would be to create a CV on Google Docs or something similar - critically, something you’re going to keep up-to-date(!) and create headings as in that article. For some of them you might have a lot, and others may not have anything yet. It’s important to do this to see a) where you can improve and focus your efforts, as well as b) giving you something to pat yourself on the back about and say “actually, I’ve achieved a lot in X area”.</p> <p>General advice: I think all of these are easier to achieve whilst a student. There! I said it. I know that many people will have other things going on at university - some will be carers, or parents, or working. However, once you start as a doctor with an average of 48h working weeks, your extra time to spend doing superfluous things is going to be even more precious. That’s not to say it’s impossible, just that it’s harder.</p> <p>For those of you further along and looking at specialty applications, the website of your chosen specialty recruitment office is your guiding document. I’ll take Core Surgical Training as an example. <a href="https://medical.hee.nhs.uk/medical-training-recruitment/medical-specialty-training/surgery/core-surgery/core-surgical-training-self-assessment-scoring-guidance-for-candidates">Here</a>’s the link to the website for 2024/2025 entry. Have a look! You will see a lot of overlap with those generic headings in Green, 2011 above.</p> <p>However, there are also extra things to think about - certain sections are either added or missing; and there is a <em>numerical score</em> attached to bits. That’s not normal CV behaviour and needs to be thought about strategically.</p> <p>It’s worth also mentioning that this is for 2024/2025 entry, and will be updated yearly. Summaries of changes are at the top of the webpage, but normally it’s nothing drastic - mainly to do with specifics around exactly how many points everything gets, rather than saying “nobody cares about audit any more”.</p> <p>For those of you applying to specialty training, use your CV template from Green, 2011 and customise it for your specialty. Move bits to the bottom if they don’t matter, and under each heading write what gets you the top possible score. This will help focus your efforts.</p> <h1 id="part-2-focussing-your-efforts">Part 2: Focussing your efforts</h1> <p>I think it’s worth keeping this article general and doing a series of posts about specific aspects of the portfolio scoring. Having said this there are some general pointers to keep in mind.</p> <h2 id="you-do-not-have-time-to-maximise-scoring-across-all-domains-unless-youve-started-in-childhoodinfancy">You do not have time to maximise scoring across all domains, unless you’ve started in childhood/infancy</h2> <p>The absolute key point here is that <em>your time is limited</em>.</p> <p>If you are reading this as a final year student or FY doctor, you do not have time to get from 0 to top points across all domains. With this in mind, make sure anything you do on top of your day job is getting you more points.</p> <p>Example: QI project</p> <p>Let’s say you’re an FY1 who did a full-cycle quality improvement project in medical school (nerd). Now, you want to apply for <a href="https://www.imtrecruitment.org.uk/recruitment-process/applying/application-scoring">Internal Medicine Training (IMT)</a>. That QI work already gets you 3 out of 4 points for the QI portion of their portfolio assessment. The only way you can get more points (that is, 4/4), is to do TWO full cycles of a QI project.</p> <p>Now you have a choice: you could continue your previous one to get another cycle out of it; if that is not feasible (for example you’re not at the same Trust for FY1) you could try and start a whole other QI project and get 2 cycles out of it; or you could decide to do neither as you have more points to gain in other aspects of the portfolio scoring system, for example you have no teaching experience at all.</p> <p>Depending on your personal situation and priorities, any one of those options might make sense. It’s just about finding how you can make the most of your limited time.</p> <h2 id="if-youve-already-maximised-a-domain-ignore-it">If you’ve already maximised a domain, ignore it</h2> <p>Let’s say you want to do <a href="https://medical.hee.nhs.uk/medical-training-recruitment/medical-specialty-training/pathology/histopathology/overview-of-histopathology/histopathology-training-self-assessment-scoring-guidance-for-applicants">Histopathology</a>, and you’ve already presented a histopathology research poster you did at a regional meeting. You’re now being offered another project to do which will likely be presented at the same regional meeting next year. Whilst this sounds great - two presentations! - you’re actually not getting any additional points for this.</p> <p>The only way this would be worth it from a portfolio perspective is for your work to be presented nationally or internationally as an oral presentation - as this would score in the “presentations/posters” section as well as the “Histopathology related activities” section. If you’re not going to do that, you should say no.</p> <p>Note, though, that each thing can only be scored in one section. For example, if you gave an oral presentation at a national conference, you couldn’t use that in both “presentations/posters” and “Histopathology related activities”. However, if you both presented a poster at a regional conference and then turned it into an international oral presentation, that would count as it would be two different activities.</p> <p>If you already have the most points you can get - either because you have the most points available of it’s not feasible to get more before the application, ignore that domain.</p> <h2 id="quality--quantity">Quality &gt; quantity</h2> <p>If you’ve already got an international oral presentation and maximised your points in that domain, you don’t get extra points for doing another one. I have met people who have done 10+ QI projects, but because none of them repeated the cycle, they don’t get maximum points. You don’t get more points for having several low-level portfolio items.</p> <p>Don’t waste time repeating things at a level which won’t get you extra points.</p> <h2 id="pushing-at-open-doors">Pushing at open doors</h2> <p>Let’s say you’re passionate about neurosurgery and are applying for <a href="https://medical.hee.nhs.uk/medical-training-recruitment/medical-specialty-training/surgery/core-surgery/core-surgical-training-self-assessment-scoring-guidance-for-candidates">CST</a> as above. Sadly, you don’t have a neurosurgery rotation that’ll get you loads of operative experience. Fortunately, you don’t need it.</p> <p>To maximise your “operative experience” score you need to be involved - i.e. scrubbed - for 40 operations. It does not specify which ones. Therefore, regardless of your surgical rotation’s specialty, you can still get this by aiming to get as much experience as possible.</p> <h1 id="part-3-putting-it-all-together">Part 3: putting it all together</h1> <p>For anything you’re going to submit for specialty recruitment applications, they may ask for proof. Create a folder on your computer, and save everything you might need to provide to prove your work. Degree certificates, QIP certificates, teaching feedback etc.</p> <p>Your folder structure should hopefully mirror your CV in this way. When you add something like a certificate, remember to update your CV. That way you’re guaranteed to be up to date with everything.</p> <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1> <ol> <li>You don’t have time to max everything unless you started very early</li> <li>If you’ve got as many points as you can in a certain domain, leave that domain alone</li> <li>You only get points for doing something once - don’t spend time repeating things unnecessarily</li> <li>Take advantages of opportunities available to you</li> </ol> <p>I hope this has been useful! I’ve been inspired to take this a little further and have individual posts about each of the common CV/portfolio domains and how to get the most out of your efforts, so please let me know if there’s anything in particular you’d like me to focus on.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="advice"/><category term="career-advice,"/><category term="portfolio"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[this file is actually called CV-maxxing.md :)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">applying for academic clinical training</title><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/applying-clinical-academic-training/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="applying for academic clinical training"/><published>2025-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/applying-clinical-academic-training</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/applying-clinical-academic-training/"><![CDATA[<p>So now we get to the application. For SFP, this has changed recently so follow your medical school’s guidance on the practical aspects. For ACF, it’s on Oriel as another application in addition to your normal specialty applications.</p> <p>Though the processes are different, the general requirements are going to be similar. Any additional research, teaching, publications, presentations, additional degrees, quality improvement you can demonstrate works in your favour.</p> <p>The best time to do this is probably medical school. The vast majority of the things on my portfolio were done between my intercalated year after year 3 and graduation. You have more time - I know it doesn’t feel like it! - than you will once you’re working full time. I hope to add posts about maximising your portfolio in the future.</p> <p>The two steps to each application are, broadly, the White Space Questions (WSQs) and the interview. The questions in each of these sections are, in my opinion, generally pretty simple to predict. There’s always going to be some rogue ones, but the majority will be straghtforward, if not easy, to prepare for.</p> <h1 id="white-space-questions">White space questions</h1> <p>These are like mini-interview questions you’ll need to type a response to in the application form on Oriel. They are there to give you an initial ‘score’ in order to invite people to interview. There are lots of resources online for this sort of thing - <a href="https://app.medall.org/contents/v-a-guide-to-whitespace-questions-wsqs-specialised-foundation-programme-series">here</a>’s one I found on MedAll, for example.</p> <p>Examples of SFP WSQs:</p> <ul> <li>Please outline your previous research experience and achievements</li> <li>What are your specific reasons for applying for a special experience programme?</li> <li>Give one example in which you have demonstrated your leadership abilities</li> </ul> <p>Examples of ACF WSQs:</p> <ul> <li>Please give details of outstanding achievements outside the field of medicine</li> <li>What experience do you have of delivering teaching?</li> <li>Describe how you believe you meet the person specification for the programme you are applying for</li> </ul> <p>I hope you’ll agree that all of these - regardless of how much you have to write in each section - are pretty obvious job-interview-type questions. If you can’t answer ‘why do you want this job’, or ‘how are you qualified for this job’, reflect more on your personal motivations - you will find something!</p> <p>As for how you find these in advance, firstly seek online resources. You can probably just think for 5 minutes and come up with some potential questions, use your CV as a framework. There’ll be something about teaching, something about your motivation, and so on. In addition, speaking to previous applicants or trainees will also help - we’re always happy to give advice and support (some of us even make websites to do so).</p> <p>The actual list for the year of application will be released at the same time as the application window opens. There’s no advantage to submitting your application early, so take as much time as possible to get them up to a good standard.</p> <p>I’d also recommend having a few people ‘on standby’ to proofread and offer editing advice. These should be people who know you’re applying; who know your CV; who know you personally, clinically and/or academically; and who have good writing skills. Tell them nice and early about this (i.e. as soon as you know you’re applying), as when the applications open you may only have 10 days to craft your responses. If someone won’t be available for such a quick turnaround, the sooner you can find a replacement the better.</p> <p>Fundamentally, the answers to these questions will come from your CV. Update this regularly, and ensure you know what you can draw upon for your answers. Maybe there’s some teaching you did in second year that you’ve forgotten about, or maybe you’re underselling your research experience. Familiarise yourself with this and it’ll be way easier to draft responses.</p> <h1 id="interviews">Interviews</h1> <p>These are always stressful. If you’re working (I was on my A+E placement), you’ll have to hope you have the day off, or a relaxed department which will allow you to take time off potentially at short notice (I remember being given a matter of days to prepare for one of my ACF interviews, which was stressful).</p> <p>If you’re going for the SFP, there is again general advice about interviews <a href="https://mindthebleep.com/sfp-introduction-to-interview/">online</a>, but please note the dates everything was written, and if in doubt about whether or not you need to prepare for an interview, ask your medical school.</p> <p>For ACFs, it’s again a straightforward process but not necessarily easy. The interview questions are freely available on the <a href="https://www.nihr.ac.uk/2025-academic-clinical-fellowships-medical-guidance-recruitment-and-appointment#tab-361726">NIHR website</a>. Obviously if you’re not a nerd, have a life, and don’t read lengthy webpages fully, you’ll miss this, but it’s literally right there. They may ask more, but they’ll always ask these.</p> <p>In general, regular interview advice applies here. Practice in advance with more questions than you think they’ll ask. There’s always some curveballs. Again, know your CV and achievements, so you can think on your feet and focus on impressing the panel. Record yourself, or work with others to develop your interview skills and present yourself in the most effective way possible.</p> <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1> <p>In summary, your application will consist of WSQs and an interview. It is possible to prepare for each.</p> <p>WSQs:</p> <ol> <li>Think about possible questions and how you’d answer them</li> <li>Assemble a ‘WSQ panel’ who can proofread and offer suggestions for improvement</li> <li>Know your CV inside out to ensure maximum benefit from each experience</li> </ol> <p>Interview:</p> <ol> <li>Think about possible questions and how you’d answer them</li> <li>For ACFs, the questions and mark schemes are literally publically available</li> <li>Practice in advance - record yourself or get a friend to practice with</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="advice"/><category term="clinical-academic-training,"/><category term="career"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[where do I even start?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">academic writing resources</title><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/academic-writing-resources/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="academic writing resources"/><published>2024-12-30T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-30T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/academic-writing-resources</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/academic-writing-resources/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="academic-writing-resources">Academic writing resources</h1> <p>I’ve collected a few resources over the years to help with any academic writing tasks, from assignments for class through to research papers. I would recommend branching out further than your own specific area of interest and seeing how other fields organise their work, as there may be someone doing something completely different to you that you could learn a lot from!</p> <h2 id="general">General</h2> <p>I’d recommend speaking to your nearest library team about this sort of thing. They’re experts in knowing which resources to go to, and often run workshops or drop-ins where you can practice and learn more. For students this will likely be your university library, but don’t sleep on your hospital library either, if you have access! I’ve attended many a Zoom workshop covering critical analysis, source finding and lots of other useful skills via my hospital library whilst at medical school.</p> <p>Here are a couple of examples of what to look for:</p> <ol> <li>My current NHS Trust, UHL, has the following sessions available at the library: [link to training calendar] (https://www.uhl-library.nhs.uk/trainingcalendar.html)</li> <li>Same thing at the hospital I was based at during university: <a href="https://www.uhsussex.nhs.uk/professionals/knowledge-and-libraries/information-skills-teaching/">University Hospitals Sussex</a></li> </ol> <p>To find these, you can google “{your hospital trust} + library services” and follow the links. If you’re having difficulty just pop them an email or visit in person!</p> <p>There’s also lots of different individuals with useful websites.</p> <p><a href="https://www.raulpacheco.org/">Dr Raul Pacheco-Vega</a> is a Full Professor in the Methods Lab of the Latin American Faculty for Social Sciences (Facultad Latinoamericana de Ciencias Sociales, FLACSO) Sede México. His website not only covers his interdisciplinary work but also includes a massive amount of advice and useful resources for anyone with academic writing tasks. From organising your work to the actual reading and writing, I’d recommend browsing through.</p> <p><a href="https://x.com/VnVrinda">Vrinda Nair</a> is a doctoral candidate at Concordia University. She has a great Twitter/X page sharing thoughts and resources to help with all aspects of academic life, from writing resources to advice on choosing colour schemes for maximum impact when presenting. There are so many threads here full of advice, have a browse.</p> <h2 id="gathering-sources">Gathering sources</h2> <p><a href="https://www.connectedpapers.com/">Connected Papers</a> is a wonderful site where for any academic paper, you can find links to others. Covering both papers referenced by your one, as well as papers which reference it, it’s a good way to get an initial handle on a field.</p> <h2 id="writing">Writing</h2> <p>Once you get to writing, <a href="https://www.phrasebank.manchester.ac.uk/">Phrasebank</a> by <a href="https://www.phrasebank.manchester.ac.uk/dr-john-morley/">Dr John Morley</a> from the University of Manchester has some excellent sentence frameworks and starters. If you’re asking the question “how do I phrase this professionally?”, “how do I say this concisely?” - this is a good place to start.</p> <h2 id="referencing">Referencing</h2> <p>I’m a fan of <a href="https://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</a> personally (especially now you can read PDFs in-app!), but this will also depend on specific projects - especially if you’re collaborating with others, it is worth it to familiarise yourself with different reference managers.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="advice,"/><category term="academic-writing"/><category term="academic-writing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[for all your academic writing needs]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">clinical academic training</title><link href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/clinical-academic-training/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="clinical academic training"/><published>2024-12-30T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-30T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/clinical-academic-training</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2024/clinical-academic-training/"><![CDATA[<p>I get a lot of questions from medical students and more junior doctors in their foundation years about clinical academic training, so I thought I’d address some points here. Hopefully you find it useful in planning your own career.</p> <h1 id="clinical-academic-training-what-is-it">Clinical academic training: what is it?</h1> <p>Broadly, clinical academic training is a way of generating clinical doctors as well as other clinicians who are also able to conduct research and work in higher education settings, for example as Professors.</p> <p>This post will focus on the UK context, as well as the medical context - i.e. this will cover the career pathway for medical doctors. It should also be noted that these pathways are constantly changing as the medical workforce planning in the UK is under constant discussion, and I’ll do my best to keep this as up-to-date as possible.</p> <p>It is also important to note that whilst this will cover the training pathway in a linear fashion, it’s not always going to be linear for everyone. It’s easiest to present the information like this but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Map%E2%80%93territory_relation">the map is not the terrain</a> and lots of people have taken lots of different routes to get to similar places.</p> <p>In essence, you can think of clinical academic training as an ‘add-on’ to your usual medical training. You apply for posts at the same time and through the same channels as usual (that’s Oriel), and you need to meet your clinical training requirements as well.</p> <p>The earliest place to get involved is through the Specialised Foundation Programme or <a href="https://foundationprogramme.nhs.uk/programmes/2-year-foundation-programme/specialised-foundation-programme/">SFP</a>. This is organised through the UK Foundation Programme Organisation or UKFPO, and you’ll apply at the same time as your normal FP application. Please read through the various parts of the website carefully - the process for 2025 changed recently, and nobody has experience of it yet.</p> <p>The SFP follows the same pattern as any other FP: 6 rotations over 2 years lasting 4 months each. These may be in any specialty, but should usually include a mix of medical and surgical work. The SFP will give you a certain amount of protected academic time - this will usually be either day release or a whole academic block. What academic time covers will be discussed below.</p> <p>After the SFP, you’ll apply for specialty training. At this stage, you’ll also be able to apply for an <a href="https://www.nihr.ac.uk/career-development/research-career-funding-programmes/predoctoral/academic-clinical-fellowship">Academic Clinical Fellowship</a>, funded by the NIHR (National Institute for Health and Care Research). This will be a separate application process</p> <h1 id="academic-time">Academic time?</h1> <p>So what do you actually <em>do</em> during your academic time? This will depend on your project(s), and your supervisor. It will also depend on the way your time is organised - day release, block release or some combination.</p> <p>During the SFP, you’ll likely be stratified into research, education or leadership tracks, which will influence your use of academic time. Education tracks will likely be doing some sort of teaching activity, revision course, simulation or similar. Research tracks will likely be doing more traditional research, for example gathering and analysing data, writing up findings and creating publications/presentations. Leadership is the track I’m least personally familiar with, but I understand it to be more along the lines of management, for example quality improvements or safety.</p> <h2 id="advantages">Advantages</h2> <p>“But Anna,” I hear you cry, “aren’t these all activities I can do <em>without</em> academic time dedicated to them?”</p> <p>Essentially, yes. I did these sorts of things at medical school without protected time, and of course things like quality improvement projects are mandatory throughout training (ask your nearest doctor, and prepare for a rant). However, when you do these things, <em>you’re not being paid to do them</em>. I’ll let you think what you will about that. You’re also having to do them in the evenings and on weekends, or other times you might want to spend resting. In summary, academic time isn’t necessary to do these activities - I knew someone who got a part-time Masters in Medical Education during FY1-FY2 - but it does make it easier.</p> <p>It also gives you time away from the wards, which anyone will tell you is a good thing. It means when you go back, you’re refreshed. It means you have a wider awareness of issues around the healthcare system rather than getting tunnel vision regarding your day-to-day. It protects you from getting burned out by the repetitive nature of some major clinical challenges - instead of having to face the misery of the A+E waiting room 10 times a shift only to see the same people waiting in corridors when you get back to work the next day, you get some time to focus on something you actually enjoy doing.</p> <p>For me, it reinforces the distinction between <em>job</em> and <em>career</em>. Yes, the day-to-day job has its ups and downs. But it helps to see certain hoops as just that - hoops to jump through to get to a better place, rather than seeing them as essentials to your work and sense of self.</p> <h2 id="disadvantages">Disadvantages</h2> <p>“Sounds amazing, I’m sold - but isn’t this too good to be true?” Another excellent point. There are certainly challenges associated with this. The main one, and if you don’t acknowledge your awareness of this in your white space questions or interviews (see <a href="https://annacasey97.github.io/blog/2025/applying-clinical-academic-training">Applying for Clinical Academic Training</a>, you’re not going to convince anyone you’re prepared, is the impact it has on your clinical training.</p> <p>Any clinical training has certain outcomes you need to meet. In FY1 and FY2 these are broad and generalisable - assessing sick patients, starting management, communicating well. I’m in O+G training now, and this year I need to demonstrate ability to take a cervical smear, and by the end of training I’ll be expected to be able to do more advanced things like complicated C sections. The requirements get gradually more demanding. Someone like me who is given 75% clinical and 25% academic time is still working full time (48h/week for doctors).</p> <p>This means my training will still take the same amount of time as my 100% clinical colleagues. In other words, I have <em>75% of the time they do</em> to reach <em>the same exact outcomes</em>.</p> <p>In contrast to someone working less than full time (LTFT) at 75% pro-rata, who will have their training extended to compensate for the additional time away from their clinical work. Yes, we’ll both have the same amount of clinical time, but they will have longer to meet the requirements than me.</p> <p>That’s the main disadvantage, and there are others. Because you’re not working the same amount of time clinically, some old-fashioned miserable people will dislike you and think you don’t take the job seriously. LTFT trainees get the same. Not all departments are like this - my current teams are all lovely - but in previous rotations and speaking to other doctors, it’s definitely not an uncommon attitude in some places. Ask at your interview, or talk to existing trainees to gauge the vibe.</p> <h1 id="summary">Summary</h1> <ol> <li>Academic clinical training is a different training pathway which sits alongside the traditional FP and specialty training routes.</li> <li>Information for these can be found online - the UKFPO website for FP, and the NIHR website beyond that</li> <li>There are advantages and disadvantages, and only you can decide if it fits within your career goals to pursue</li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="advice"/><category term="clinical-academic-training,"/><category term="career"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[what is it? and what's the point?]]></summary></entry></feed>